<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='rcs-fast-import.1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>rcs-fast-import</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>Nov 11 2010</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='productname'>rcs-fast-import</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>rcs-fast-import</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Development Tools</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>rcs-fast-import</refname>
<refpurpose>unpack a fast-import stream into an RCS repository tree</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>rcs-fast-import</command>
  <arg choice='opt'>-v</arg>
  <arg choice='opt'>-u</arg>
  <arg choice='opt'>-l</arg>
  <arg choice='opt'>-p</arg>
  <arg choice='opt'>-V</arg>
  <arg choice='opt'>-?</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>This tool breaks the content of a git-fast-import stream on
stdin into individual RCS master files in RCS subdirectories of the
corresponding directory structure.</para>

<para>Normally, all import-stream per-commit metadata that RCS cannot
represent natively is written into each comment as RFC-822 mail
headers, followed by a blank line; this includes mark, committer and
author data, mark cross-references to parent commits, and extension
properties. The -p option suppresses this, producing a plain RCS
comment.</para>

<para>With the -v option, emit a twirling-baton prompt during stream read and
do not suppress progess messages from the RCS tools.</para>

<para>With the -l option, check out and lock all resulting files at their latest
revisions; with the -u option, check out but do not lock.  With neither
option, the RCS subdirectories and masters are created but no working
copies checked out.</para>

<para>The -V option displays the program version number and exits. -? displays
a help message and exits.</para>

<para>In order to preserve history, D file operations do not delete
previously-created master files; instead, an empty file is checked in
as the content and the file's RCS state tag is set to "Deleted".  R
file operations copy corresponding RCS master files <emphasis>without
</emphasis> deleting the old master file; instead, an empty fiile is
checked in as the content and the state set to "Renamed". C operations
initialize a new file.</para>

<para>Import-stream branches are mapped to RCS revision branch structure.
Each RCS master poduced will include a list of branch tags, each of which
has the value of the corresponding RCS branch identifier for that file.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>The following limitations are inherent in the RCS format:</para>

<para>Annotated tags cannot be preserved in a format readily accessible
to RCS. This tool deposits them as tagged revisions of a file named
<filename>ANNOTATED-TAGS</filename> in the toplevel RCS
directory.</para>

<para>In each commit, the committer date entered in RCS metadata will
be the committer date from the import stream, but the committer
identity will be lost; all commits are checked in as if by the
invoking user and identified with the invoking user's login name.
(However, this tool preserves complete attribution in comment headers
unless the -p option was selected.)</para>

<para>Lightweight tags and branches may cause errors in older RCS versions,
as they are saved with their full (path) names, including slashes.</para>

<para>Submodule links ("M" entries mith mode 160000) and symlinks ("M"
entries mith mode 120000) can't be handled; the tool will throw an
error if it sees one.</para>

<para>The following are implementation limits of this tool which may be 
fixed in a future release:</para>

<para>This tool has not been tested with RCS versions earlier than
5.7.  It is likely older versions will throw errors on some tag and
branch names that are legal in fast-import files.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='returns'><title>ERROR RETURNS</title>
<para>Returns 1 on any error, 0 otherwise.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@thyrsus.com</email>; project page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/rcs-fast-import'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/rcs-fast-import</ulink>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
